Ziyu Yao

🕆 ziyuyao.org 🖂 ziyuyao@gmu.edu 💆 ZiyuYao GScholar

Department of Computer Science George Mason University Nguyen Engineering Building 4415 Fairfax, VA 22030 USA

(Last update: April 23, 2023)

Research Interests

I am interested in broad natural language processing and artificial intelligence problems. In particular, my current research explores building natural language interfaces (e.g., question answering systems) that can interact with humans while assisting them in knowledge discovery and task completion. Some of my work is about interdisciplinary research topics, such as AI/NLP for Software Engineering, Healthcare, and Psychology.

Education

2015–2021 M.S./Ph.D., The Ohio State University (OSU), Computer Science & Engineering. (Thesis: On Advancing Natural Language Interfaces: Data Collection, Model Development, and User Interaction. Advisor: Prof. Huan Sun)

2011–2015 **B.E.**, Beijing University of Posts and Telecommunications (BUPT), Communication Engineering.

Professional Experience

2021-present Assistant Professor, George Mason University (GMU).

Affiliation: C4I & Cyber Center, Center for Advancing Human-Machine Partnership, and Institute for Digital InnovAtion (IDIA) at GMU

2021 Summer Research Intern, Microsoft Semantic Machines (Mentor: Anthony Platanios).

2020 Summer Research Intern, LTI, Carnegie Mellon University (Mentor: Graham Neubig).

2018 Summer Research Intern, Microsoft Research, Redmond (Mentor: Yizhe Zhang, Bill Dolan).

2017 Summer Research Intern, Fujitsu Lab of America (Mentor: Mehdi Bahrami, Wei-Peng Chen).

2014–2015 Research Intern, Tsinghua University, Beijing (Mentor: Minlie Huang).

Awards and Honors

- 2021 **Best Paper Award**, The IEEE International Conference on Bioinformatics and Biomedicine (BIBM).
- 2021 Graduate Student Research Award, OSU, CSE.
- 2020 Presidential Fellowship, OSU.
- 2020 Rising Star in EECS, UC Berkeley.
- 2020 Graduate Students Poster Award (Honorable Mention), CSE, OSU.
- 2019 NSF Student Travel Award, The Web Conference (WWW).
- 2019 Graduate Students Poster Award (Honorable Mention), CSE, OSU.
- 2018 Travel Grant for Graduate Cohort for Women, San Francisco, CRA-W.
- 2015 Beijing Outstanding Graduate Award, Beijing, China.
- 2012, 2014 First-class Scholarship (top 3%), BUPT, China.
 - 2013 **Second-class Scholarship (top 5%)**, BUPT, China.

Publications

*my advisee; †equal contribution.

- Daking Rai*, Yilun Zhou, Bailin Wang, **Ziyu Yao**, "Explaining Large Language Model-based Neural Semantic Parsers", to appear at **AAAI 2023 (Student Abstract)**.
- Philseok Lee, Shea Fyffe, Mina Son, Zihao Jia, and Ziyu Yao, "A paradigm shift from "human writing" to "machine generation" in personality test development: An application of state-of-the-art natural language processing", Journal of Business and Psychology 2022. [Paper]
- Tianbao Xie[†], Chen Henry Wu[†], Peng Shi, Ruiqi Zhong, Torsten Scholak, Michihiro Yasunaga, Chien-Sheng Wu, Ming Zhong, Pengcheng Yin, Sida Wang, Victor Zhong, Bailin Wang, Chengzu Li, Connor Boyle, Ansong Ni, Ziyu Yao, Dragomir Radev, Caiming Xiong, Lingpeng Kong, Rui Zhang, Noah A. Smith, Luke Zettlemoyer, Tao Yu, "UnifiedSKG: Unifying and Multi-Tasking Structured Knowledge Grounding with Text-to-Text Language Models", to appear at The 2022 Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing (EMNLP 2022). [Preprint, Code, Project Website]
- Wenhu Chen, Xinyun Chen, Zhiyu Chen, Ziyu Yao, Michihiro Yasunaga, Tao Yu, Rui Zhang, "Proceedings of the Workshop on Structured and Unstructured Knowledge Integration (SUKI)", co-located at NAACL 2022. [Workshop Proceedings, Website]
- Peizhao Li, Xuchao Zhang, Ziyu Yao, Wei Cheng, Haifeng Chen, Hongfu Liu, "Code Editing from Few Exemplars by Adaptive Multi-Extent Composition", The Deep Learning for Code Workshop at The Tenth International Conference on Learning Representations (ICLR 2022 DL4Code). [Paper]
- Xiang Yue, Ziyu Yao, Huan Sun, "Synthetic Question Value Estimation for Domain Adaptation of Question Answering", The 60th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL 2022, acceptance rate: 20.75%). [Paper, Code]
- Ziyu Yao, "On Advancing Natural Language Interfaces: Data Collection, Model Development, and User Interaction", The Ohio State University, PhD Dissertation, 2021. [Dissertation]
- **Ziyu Yao**, Frank Xu, Pengcheng Yin, Huan Sun, Graham Neubig, "Learning Structural Edits via Incremental Tree Transformations", The Ninth International Conference on Learning Representations (**ICLR 2021**). [Paper, Code]
- Ziyu Yao, Yiqi Tang, Scott Wen-tau Yih, Huan Sun, Yu Su, "An Imitation Game for Learning Semantic Parsers from User Interaction", 2020 Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing (EMNLP 2020, acceptance rate: 22.4%). [Paper, Code]
- Xiang Yue, Xinliang Frederick Zhang, Ziyu Yao, Simon Lin, Huan Sun, "CliniQG4QA: Generating Diverse Questions for Domain Adaptation of Clinical Question Answering", IEEE BIBM 2021 (Best Paper Award). [Paper, Code]
- Royi Lachmy, Ziyu Yao, Greg Durrett, Milos Gligoric, Junyi Jessy Li, Ray Mooney, Graham Neubig, Yu Su, Huan Sun, Reut Tsarfaty, "Proceedings of the 1st Workshop on Natural Language Processing for Programming (NLP4Prog 2021)", co-located at ACL-IJCNLP 2021. [Workshop Proceedings, Website]
- Ziyu Yao, Yu Su, Huan Sun, Scott Wen-tau Yih, "Model-based Interactive Semantic Parsing: A Unified Formulation and A Text-to-SQL Case Study", 2019 Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing (EMNLP 2019, acceptance rate: 23.8%). [Paper, Code]
- Boyuan Pan, Hao Li, Ziyu Yao, Deng Cai, Huan Sun, "Reinforced Dynamic Reasoning for Conversational Question Generation", Proceedings of the 57th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL 2019, acceptance rate: 25.7%).
 [Paper, Code]

- Ziyu Yao, Jayavardhan Reddy Peddamail, Huan Sun, "CoaCor: Code Annotation for Code Retrieval with Reinforcement Learning", The Web Conference 2019 (WWW 2019, acceptance rate: 18%). [Paper, Code]
- Ziyu Yao, Xiujun Li, Jianfeng Gao, Brian Sadler, Huan Sun, "Interactive Semantic Parsing for If-Then Recipes via Hierarchical Reinforcement Learning", The AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence 2019 (AAAI 2019, acceptance rate: 16.2%; SPOTLIGHT). [Paper, Code]
- Ziyu Yao, Yizhe Zhang, Xiujun Li, Jianfeng Gao, Michel Galley, Chris Brockett, Huan Sun, Bill Dolan, "IEC: Towards Interest-Eliciting Neural Conversational Agents", Manuscript 2019, [Paper].
- Jayavardhan Reddy Peddamail, Ziyu Yao, Zhen Wang, Huan Sun, "A Comprehensive Study of StaQC for Deep Code Summarization", SIGKDD 2018 Deep Learning Day. [Paper]
- Ziyu Yao, Daniel S. Weld, Wei-Peng Chen, Huan Sun, "StaQC: A Systematically Mined Question-Code Dataset from Stack Overflow", The Web Conference 2018 (WWW 2018, acceptance rate: 14.8%). [Paper, Code]
- Li Zhao, Minlie Huang, Ziyu Yao, Rongwei Su, Yingying Jiang, Xiaoyan Zhu. "Semi-Supervised Multinomial Naive Bayes for Text Classification by Leveraging Word-Level Statistical Constraint", The AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence 2016 (AAAI 2016, acceptance rate: 25.8%). [Paper]
- Ziyu Yao, Shouzhong Tu, Minlie Huang, Xiaoyan Zhu. "A Semi-Supervised Method for Filtering Chinese Spam Tweets". Journal of Chinese Information Processing 2016, 30(5): 176-186. [Paper in Chinese]

Talks

- 2022 **Challenges in Constructing Human-centric Natural Language Interfaces**, <u>Invited</u> talk at the GMU Statistics Department. Host: Nicholas Rios.
- 2022 On Building Natural Language Interfaces for "Humans", Invited talk at ServiceNow Research, Canada (virtually). Host: Dzmitry Bahdanau.
- 2022 **Building Interactive and Adaptive Question Answering Systems**, <u>Invited talk</u> at CLSP (Center for Language and Speech Processing) Seminar, Johns Hopkins University. Host: Kevin Duh, Ben Van Durme.
- 2022 **Building Interactive and Adaptive Question Answering Systems**, Invited talk at Center for Advancing Human-Machine Partnership, George Mason University.
- 2021 **Building Interactive Natural Language Interfaces**, <u>Invited talk</u> at Brandeis University (virtually). Host: Hongfu Liu.
- 2021 Building Interactive Natural Language Interfaces, OSU AI Club (virtually).
- 2020 An Imitation Game for Learning Semantic Parsers from User Interaction, EMNLP (virtually).
- 2020 On Building an Interactive Natural Language Interface: An intelligent agent that can communicate, collaborate and learn, Invited talk at Microsoft Research Al Breakthroughs Workshop (virtually). Invited by: Ahmed Hassan Awadallah, Alex Polozov.
- 2020 **Building Natural Language Interfaces to Programs**, <u>Invited talk</u> at VMware, Beijing (virtually). Host: Jin He, Kevin Song.
- 2020 **Towards Building Interactive and Collaborative Natural Language Interfaces**, Invited talk at NeuLab, Carnegie Mellon University (virtually). Host: Graham Neubig.
- 2020 Learning Semantic Parsers from User Interaction, CSE AI Seminar, OSU.

- 2019 Towards Building Interactive and Collaborative Natural Language Interfaces, Invited talk at Chair of Management Information System, ETH Zurich, Host: Stefan Feuerriegel.
- 2019 CoaCor: Code Annotation for Code Retrieval with Reinforcement Learning, WWW, San Francisco, USA.
- 2019 Interactive Semantic Parsing for If-Then Recipes via Hierarchical Reinforcement Learning, AAAI, Hawaii, USA.
- 2018 Interactive Semantic Parsing for If-Then Recipes via Hierarchical Reinforcement Learning, CSE Al Seminar, OSU.
- 2018 StaQC: A Systematically Mined Question-Code Dataset from Stack Overflow, WWW, Lyon, France.

Grants

"NSF Convergence Accelerator Track G: Secure Texting over Non-cooperative Networks and Anti-jamming Enhancement in 5G", National Science Foundation, 09/2022-07/2023. Role: Senior Personnel.

"Securing Interactions between Humans and Machines", The Commonwealth Cyber Initiative (CCI) at Virginia, \$60,000, 12/2022-12/2023. Role: Pl.

"Al Engineering Seedlings", US Department of Defense, contract from UMD Applied Research Laboratory for Intelligence and Security (ARLIS), \$100,000, 07/2021–07/2022. Role: Co-PI.

Teaching Experience

At GMU:

2023 Fall CS678: Advanced Natural Language Processing.

2023 Spring CS478: Natural Language Processing.

2022 Fall CS678: Advanced Natural Language Processing.

2022 Spring **CS499: Natural Language Processing.**

2021 Fall CS695: Special Topics on Natural Language Processing.

At OSU:

2020 Fall CSE Panel: Graduate School Experience and Expectation, CSE, OSU. Panelist.

2020 Fall Foundations of Speech and Language Processing, CSE, OSU. Guest lecturer.

2018 Fall Course Panel: Data Management in the Cloud, CSE, OSU. Guest panelist.

2017 Spring Introduction to Computer Programming in C++, CSE, OSU. Student instructor.

Mentoring Experience

Mentored PhD Students.

Daking Rai (Spring'22-)

Saurabh Srivastava (Spring'22-)

Hao Yan (Spring'22-)

Long Doan (Fall'22-)

Murong Yue (Fall'22-)

Mohamed Aghzal (Spring'23-, co-advised w/ Erion Plaku)

Mentored/Collaborated Master Students.

Gaurav Singh (Spring'22)

Janit Bidhan (Fall'22)

Mentored/Collaborated Undergraduate Students.

Mariana Ritchie (Spring'22)

Brian Meike (Spring'22)

Soumithri Gadepalli (Spring'22)

(Co-)Mentored/Collaborated Students (at OSU).

Jayavardhan Reddy Peddamail (Master Student; now at Google)

Varun Ranganathan Dhanvanth (Master Student; now at Facebook)

Heming Sun (Undergraduate Student)

Tianshu Zhang (PhD Student)

Leslie Zhou (Master Student)

School/Department Services

Department Committees.

PhD Recruiting Committee (Fall'22 - Spring'23)

Faculty Search Committee (Fall'21 - Spring'22)

Comprehensive Exam Committees.

Fahim Faisal (Fall'22)

Jonathan Mbuya (Fall'22)

Joost Bottenbley (Fall'22)

Md Mahfuz Ibn Alam (Spring'22)

Abhisekh Rana (Spring'22)

Professional Activities

Outreach Services.

Girls Who Code chapter at Chantilly High School: invited speaker	2023
Science and Engineering Fair at Thomas Jefferson High School: faculty judge	2023
SIGKDD Undergraduate Consortium: faculty mentor	2022
Editor Services.	
ACM SIGAI: Newsletter co-editor	2022 -
Organizing Committees.	
MASC-SLL: Mid-Atlantic Student Colloquium on Speech, Language and Learning	2023
in to e ozz. This relative obtains consquant on opecen, zanguage und zeuring	-025

Area Chairs or Senior Program Committees.

NLP4Prog at ACL'21: The First Workshop on NLP for Programming

ACL: Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics	2023
AAAI: The AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence	2023
FMNLP: Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing	2022

SUKI at NAACL'22: Workshop on Structured and Unstructured Knowledge Integration 2022

2021

Reviewers (Journal).

<u>TKDD</u> : ACM Transactions on Knowledge Discovery from Data	2022 –
TKDE: IEEE Transactions on Knowledge and Data Engineering	2022 -

Program Committees/Reviewers (Conference). ARR: ACL Rolling Review MSR: Mining Software Repositories Conference NAACL: Annual Conference of the North American Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics EMNLP: Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing 2018, 202	2021 - 2021 2021
AAAI: The AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence	2020
NLPCC: Conference on Natural Language Processing and Chinese Computing CoNLL: Conference on Computational Natural Language Learning	2020 2020 2019
Secondary/External Reviewer: ACL: Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics 201 KDD: SIGKDD Conference on Knowledge Discovery and Data Mining 2017, 201 NAACL: Annual Conference of the North American Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics	8, 2020 9, 2020 2019
	.6, 2018
<u>WWW</u> : International World Wide Web Conference <u>CIKM</u> : International Conference on Information and Knowledge Management	2017 2016
Program Committees/Reviewers (Workshop).	
InterNLP at NeurIPS 2022: Workshop on Interactive Learning for Natural La Processing BigData-IT at IEEE BigData 2022: Workshop on Knowledge Discovery and Data Mil IT Operations HCI+NLP at NAACL 2022: Bridging Human-Computer Interaction and Natural La Processing DL4Code at ICLR 2022: Deep Learning for Code IntEx-SemPar at EMNLP 2020: Interactive and Executable Semantic Parsing Workshop	2022 ining on 2022 anguage 2022 2022
NLI at ACL 2020: Natural Language Interface Workshop SRW at ACL 2019: Student Research Workshop	2020 2019